You take the south side.
I'll take north.
You met the new boss yet?
I heard he's young.
Watch for any potential
threats to the mayor.
Younger than us, and he's got
limited field experience.
[Lisbon]
'Mayor just left the building.
The march is underway.'
Copy that.
Moving into position.
Doesn't it bother you, working
with a barely qualified guy?
You get used to it.
[woman screams]
I've got an unknown disturbance
in the northeast alley.
- Excuse me. Police.
- CBI.
- Coming through.
- Excuse me.
- You see what happened?
- No. Lo vi en el suelo.
Anybody see what happened?
Alguien vio lo que paso?
Okay, I need for you
to secure the alley.
Get backup in here now. Contact
the mayor's security detail.
Clear these people out now.
He's dead.
- 'Excuse me.'
- 'Excuse me. Watch out.'
What do we got?
Homicide.
Multiple stab wounds.
- Any ID?
- No wallet, nothing I can see.
Got a large transient
population. Could be a robbery.
- Inform the office.
- Sure.
Jane.
[indistinct shouting]
Speak up, Lisbon.
It's a little loud here.
- Are you close to us?
- Well, that depends.
Are you still on crowd patrol?
No. We got a homicide now.
Then I'm close.
[indistinct shouting]
[distorted indistinct shouting]
[indistinct conversations]
[siren wailing]
[Lisbon]
'Hey, Jane!'
Strange time for murder. In
the middle of a protest march?
Leave it to a killer to do
something crazy.
Or calculated.
Notice how this alleyway
is starting to look like
a policeman's ball?
If I wanted to use a bullet
to express my displeasure
with the mayor's politics,
I'd clear out the heat.
You think this murder
is a decoy?
No clue, but there's
a suspicious-looking man
on "J" street and 56th.
Haunted eyes, nervous energy,
an overcoat on a hot day.
That's thin, even for you.
Yeah, you're probably right.
It's only the mayor's life
at stake. Forget I spoke.
Cho.
[indistinct conversations]
[chanting in Spanish]
We got him.
Southeast corner.
[chanting in Spanish continues]
CBI. Put your hands
where I can see 'em.
Do me a favor and step
over here with me.
What's the problem, ma'am?
I didn't do anything.
Then you won't mind
if we search you.
Hands on your head,
interlace your fingers.
Turn around
and face the wall.
[chanting in Spanish continues]
Gun.
A semiautomatic .45.
[clicks]
Fully loaded.
[click]
Chambered round.
I can explain that.
Station's right around
the corner. Turn around.
[handcuffs click]
Come on.
[chanting in Spanish continues]
[theme music]
That's a concealed carry license
and that's my name. Henry Tibbs.
Gives me authority to carry my
sidearm anywhere in California.
These aren't easy
to come by.
You had to demonstrate
a need to carry.
I'm a Texas man.
That's my need.
Met a local sheriff
who sympathized.
Hook 'em horns.
Why were you standing there
with your legal
concealed sidearm?
I was, uh, downtown,
dropping off resumes.
I'm, uh, an insurance salesman.
I've been out of work.
The economy's tighter
than bark on a tree.
You always go job hunting
with a loaded gun?
There were several hundred
angry protesters on that street.
And you put yourself
right in the middle of 'em.
Sure. It's not every day
you get to see a big-city mayor.
[Cho]
'Or shoot him.'
Henry Tibbs.
Clean record, no priors.
Gun permit checks out.
Says here
he's on unemployment
owns a home
with his wife Linda
but they're behind
on payments.
And the sun came up
just to hear him crow
as they say in Texas.
Do we have anything
that connects Tibbs
to our John Doe
in the alley?
Not yet. Forensics swabbed him
for bloodstains.
Couldn't find anything.
I don't like what I'm hearing.
Police put out an alert
for a hate crime
so we rounded up
the nearest white guy.
And while that's a refreshing
twist on racial profiling
Mr. Tibbs has himself
grounds for a lawsuit.
We should let him go
and send his wife some flowers.
Special agent Luther Wainright.
I'm your new boss.
Welcome aboard.
I'm Agent Lisbon.
Agent Lisbon,
nice to meet you.
- This is Agent Rig--
- Agent Rigsby.
- Pleasure to meet you.
- Van Pelt.
I've read everyone's file,
so I kind of know..
Patrick Jane. Still making
my way through yours.
It's a little bit
heavier reading.
Yeah, do me a favor.
Don't tell me how it ends.
[chuckles]
Uh, hard times, everyone, um,
for the entire unit
but, uh, things are about to get
a whole lot easier.
I pride myself on two things,
trust and transparency.
Excellent, so you'll
tell us how old you are?
Rigsby here is running
an office pool.
I'm not running a pool.
Henry Tibbs. What's the plan?
I suggest that we release him
and keep him under surveillance.
Yeah, that sounds reasonable.
Keep me posted.
Oh, um, your John Doe,
he may be a photographer.
On long shoot days, that bandage
on the bridge of his nose
would keep the nose pads
on his eyeglasses
from digging into his skin.
We'll check it out.
Excellent. Thank you.
Sharp.
This is the surveillance car
you chose?
We can't take an official
vehicle. We need to blend in.
Okay, and, uh, this blends in?
Nobody's forcing you
to go on this surveillance.
You're right. Good point,
but I'm coming anyway.
Did you bring a disguise?
[car door opens]
"Did I bring a disguise?"
So Wainright was spot-on.
I checked
a professional directory
for local photographers,
there he was. Scott Gibson.
Spoke to the magazine
he works for.
He was shooting
a photo essay of the homeless.
- Do we know anything else?
- Clean record.
Lives alone,
no family to speak of
always carries a cell phone
on assignment.
There was no phone
at the crime scene or a camera.
Your robbery theory
is looking better.
Let's hope so. Got a GPS track
on Gibson's phone.
Residential neighborhood,
south of here.
Way to bury the lead.
- Let's go.
- Okay.
[engine rumbling]
[engine turns off]
[Patrick sighs]
'Okay.'
[exhales deeply]
So what now?
Now we wait.
Wait for what?
For Tibbs to come back out.
That's no fun. I thought
the point of surveillance
was to, uh, surveil.
It's hard to do that
from inside a car.
Well, I can't go in there.
Tibbs might recognize me.
Mm. That is a problem.
Well, he's never met me.
Problem solved.
I'm gonna need these.
Hey.
Jane.
[indistinct conversations]
[southern accent]
Bourbon. Big one.
Bigger than all hell
and half of Texas.
A lone star man, huh?
Yeah, what's it to ya, hoss?
[chuckles]
I seen you before.
Yeah?
Yeah. Let me think.
"Soldier of fortune", weaponry
convention, Vegas, 2004.
Nope.
No? Well, that's too bad.
That was full-auto
rock 'n' roll mayhem
in the desert, my friend.
Uzis, floozies, and Jacuzzis.
Weaponry convention, huh?
Mm.
One of the greatest weekends
of my life
and I've had some weekends.
No offense, pal. You don't look
like a weapons enthusiast.
You wanna catch chickens,
you don't look like a fox.
Am I right?
Damn straight, I'm right.
What's your weapon of choice?
A loaded one.
Can I get another
and one here for my friend?
The cell phone signal came
from this house.
Foreclosure property.
Door's ajar.
[whispers]
You ready?
[door creaks]
Hey, back here.
Hey, wake up.
Wake up!
Hands. Raise 'em high!
You have any weapons?
- No, sir. I don't believe so.
- What about a cell phone?
I believe
I got one in my bag.
Keep your hands up.
I'll find them.
[bag rustling]
You look familiar.
What's your name?
Willie.
- Not Willie Shubert.
- You know this guy?
He's a Bay Area Legend.
I had a bootleg of his first CD.
It was all I listened to
in college.
I always wondered
what happened to you.
Listen up here, Willie.
Some of the stuff you're
carrying came off a dead man.
Well, that's not good.
Neither is the dried blood
on your shirt.
'How'd that get there?'
Well, let's see. Uh..
I got the blood on me
when I was stabbing
that fella in the alley.
A trueman, a realman has
but one purpose in this world.
- He lives to fight.
- That's what I'm talking about.
It doesn't matter who he is
what status the world puts,
it's what's in here that counts.
- Mm-hmm.
- Fighting the enemy.
Combating evil.
- Mm-hmm.
- That's nobility.
That's what makes
a man a hero!
Amen, brother.
I'm pretty much done here.
What kinda evil
are you fighting, mostly?
Why do you care?
I don't even know you.
[chuckles]
I don't know you either
but I like you.
Come here.
I wanna show you somethin'.
[alarm chirps]
Check that out.
Remington 700.
That is nice.
You carry this around
in your car?
Never know when
a grizzly bear might appear.
Go on. Feel the weight
of that honey.
[clears throat]
Oh.
That's nice.
[Patrick]
'Yeah, makes you wonder,
doesn't it?'
What it'd feel like
to take that shot?
What, on a human being?
We live in a target-rich
environment, my friend.
'It'd be soeasy.'
[chuckles]
Yes, it would.
And you are
a full-on psycho, my friend.
I'm hammered. I'm gonna, um..
Give me that here.
- I'm gonna walk home tonight.
- Get outta here.
Stay frosty.
[inhales deeply]
[exhales deeply]
Let's go. Lisbon's called off
the surveillance on Tibbs.
They think they've found
their killer.
I know I found mine.
I thought I saw something
in Tibbs' eyes yesterday
but I wanted to make sure,
last night I did.
What'd you see?
He's a man on autopilot.
Set to kill.
If we weren't there to stop him
yesterday, I'm confident
he would've pulled the trigger.
- You got that from his eyes?
- Pretty much.
I'm not doubting you.
I'm just...fascinated.
Well, there was the tension
in his body as well
and the overcoat,
but, uh...the eyes were enough.
The trouble is, I mean,
even if you are right
we can't arrest an offender
before he's offended.
It's better than after,
don't you think?
See, here's the problem
with working homicide.
There's so much death.
Tibbs is a man on the verge.
He's a man
on the threshold of murder
possibly even mass murder.
Now who wouldn't wanna try
and stop that kind of nightmare?
Theoretical criminology.
I took that class.
I think it's fascinating.
Uh, it just has
no practical value.
No practical value? I guess the
same could be said
for middle management
bureaucrats.
Chafe as you may, against
the bridle of responsibility
we can't shortchange
due process.
Now, following
a potential offender around
is a waste of resources.
Yeah, you're right.
What we need here
is a confidence trick.
A what?
Scam. Hustle. Bunco. Flimflam.
If we can get inside
the world of Henry Tibbs
then I can predict
when and where he will blow.
All we have to do is pop out and
arrest him for attempted murder.
Before we go
too far down this path
I'm not ready to rule out Tibbs
as an actual murder suspect.
'Didn't Willie Shubert confess?'
Yes, he did,
but I don't believe him.
Look at his history.
Mental illness,
substance abuse, vagrancy.
Exactly, and he was covered
in the victim's blood
and in possession
of his belongings.
Yes, b-but there's
no record of violence.
I think that his confession
was a cry for help.
- Willie didn't hurt anyone.
- How do you know that?
You kind of have
to hear him play the saxophone.
I love it, Lisbon.
The beautiful soul defense.
'You two want me believe'
that a man who confessed
to murder did nothing
and a man who did nothing
is a murderer?
You may even be smarter
than you look.
I think Tibbs is a dead end
but I like to reward passion,
so...go prove me wrong.
You have 24 hours
to demonstrate
that Tibbs poses
an imminent danger
and I'm sending
the Shubert case to the DA.
What about my passion?
I called my shot.
Excuse me.
Okay, the goal is
to get close to Tibbs
to figure out
when he will snap.
We're gonna play this...
like a long con.
Rigsby, your objective is
to exploit
the mark's dreams and desires.
Uh, the one thing
we do know about Tibbs..
...he desires a job.
Now according
to Van Pelt's research
he's already gone downtown
and applied for one
at the Goldwyn Insurance Group.
They've rejected
his application
but Tibbs doesn't know that yet
so we need the Goldwyn Group
to lend us a meeting room
so we can conduct
a fake job interview.
We also need to know about his family life or lack thereof.
It seems the lady of the house, Linda Tibbs
has filed for a divorce.
We need to know why.
So, Van Pelt, you'll find out where she works
and you will make contact.
Cho, I think it's best
you ditch the race car
and find something
a little more modest
to keep the mark
under surveillance.
Let's have fun.
Good luck to all.
'Your first CD.'
Only CD.
I still have it.
Back in college, whenever
I missed my family in Chicago
I would listen to it.
It helped.
I've been doing
some research on you, Willie.
Not long after you made
this album, you lost your wife.
'Car accident, right?'
You were driving? Is that
why you stopped playing?
What do you want?
Why you confessed to a murder
you didn't commit.
I don't know what you're talking
about. I stuck that boy!
Ready to get
what I got coming.
You need to understand
the reality
of what's going on, Willie.
The DA will put you
in prison.
[scoffs]
I'm old, tired
of sleeping in alleys.
I ain't got no place to go.
Prison's someplace.
And a lethal injection is part
of the vacation package.
You'll get three hots
and a cot
just for stealing off
a dead body.
What do you say
we come clean on this
so we can keep you alive?
Okay, yeah.
Tell me what happened
yesterday.
That fellow that took my photo
earlier in the day had..
...gave me $20
for my photo rights
but when I found him dead
his wallet was laying
on the ground, empty.
Why did you take it?
It's real leather.
And what about the camera?
What happened to that?
I found the cell phone
in his jacket pocket.
I didn't see no camera.
I'm gonna get you out of this,
whether you like it or not.
Thank you.
[receiver clatters]
- You ready? He's here.
- Not really.
Have a seat, please.
Mr. Rigsby will be right in.
He's one
of our senior executives.
'What do you want me
to ask him?'
Ask him whatever you want.
You're charming.
Just get him to open up.
Okay.
The questions
that Agent Wainright gave me?
- Wainright gave you questions?
- Yeah.
He says they're designed
to elicit a patterned response
to determine
antisocial personality disorder.
Well, maybe they'll make you
sound extra-smart just like him.
Okay. Wish me luck.
You'll be fine.
Just don't be yourself.
Whoa. Hang on.
What is that?
That is a large pimple forming
above your brow there.
I don't know. Is there?
Actually, no.
It looks more like a melanoma.
- What? Are you sure?
- No, I'm not.
You should get that checked out
as soon as you can.
- Now run along.
- Mm-hmm.
[door opens]
[closes door]
- Hi.
- Hello, Mr. Tibbs.
Wayne Rigsby.
Named after the duke himself.
Yeah, my dad liked his westerns.
A man after my own heart.
My family's been raising
crops, cattle, and children
in Texas for two centuries.
So, Mr. Tibbs,
uh, what kind of..
'what kind of an employee
would you describe yourself as?'
- Can I get you a drink?
- No, thank you.
I'm here to talk about
your husband Henry.
Grace Van Pelt with the CBI.
[sighs]
What'd he do?
Nothing yet,
but we have reason
to believe that
he might be dangerous.
"Might be"?
That's a good one.
Talk to me.
No, ma'am. I have been
talking for a long time
and I am tired
of nobody listening.
Look, I don't know
who you've been talking to
but I'll take you seriously.
No.
I am not getting lured back
into this again.
I even had a judge turn me away
for being the unstable one.
I'm taking care of myself
from now on.
Rachel, can you cover
this table for me, please?
I have a Master's
in Forensic Psych.
The questions
I gave Rigsby came
from a standardized test
to diagnose psychopathy.
Tricking our mark into taking
a mental health test.
Nice touch.
Just embracing
your spirit of the con.
I cross-referenced Tibbs'
answers with his background.
Do you have any idea
what the test revealed?
No, but I can't wait
to find out.
Nothing.
No evidence of
criminal psychopathy whatsoever.
Tibbs is just
an out-of-work insurance broker.
A monster without conscience,
void of any human empathy.
- Jane.
- Hey, tests can be fooled.
Human behavior never lies.
Normal people,
they can't help but imitate
what happens
in their social world.
One of the most
mimicked behaviors..
...face-touching.
Observe Agent Rigsby,
as neurotic as a border collie.
He can't stop touching his face.
Now Tibbs, his hands never
leave the table, not once.
That's, uh, quite a leap.
Is it?
Look how you're sitting
right now.
You're leaning back with your
legs crossed, just like me.
Oh, please,
but I always sit this way.
You do? Oh.
Hmm. Maybe you're right.
Of course I'm right.
See? You're normal.
That man has the conscience
of a mollusk.
[no audio]
Hey, Tibbs.
- I'm with him.
- Alright. Go ahead.
[engine turns off]
[gunshot]
[gunshots]
[laughs]
Hey. Bad year for Merlot.
'That's my case. You can, uh..'
You can try to hit one,
if you want.
Okay.
Thanks.
No problem.
[machine gunfire]
[cheering]
[indistinct conversations]
Suspect was shooting zombies
with an illegal M240 Bravo
belt-fed, gas-operated.
Zombies?
Lifelike targets. Mannequins.
- No wonder Tibbs' wife left.
- What'd you learn?
She wouldn't talk, but according
to a protective order
she filed in May,
they got into a fight.
He took a hammer to the bedroom.
Blamed her for his failures.
I'm sorry. I don't remember
a protective order.
Judge denied it, said Linda's
request wasn't specific enough
to constitute an emergency.
She's scared of him
but can't get anyone
to take her seriously.
One, Tibbs is living
a life of failure
two, he's socially isolated,
three, he owns firearms
and four,
his wife just left him.
Classic 4-pointed profile
of a mass shooter.
We'll arrest Henry Tibbs
on a felony weapons charge
then we can insist
on counseling.
What happens in a couple months
when he hits the streets?
He reports to parole.
We all know
how effective that is.
- There is no ideal system.
- Sure, there is.
We follow Tibbs,
and catch him in the act
of attempted mass murder.
Jury puts him away for life.
It's that simple.
You are quite the Pied Piper,
Mr. Jane. Quite the salesman.
I happen to think counseling
is our best option right now.
All due respect, chief,
but isn't it worth a shot?
I will not follow around
an almost-bad guy
just waiting for him
to snap.
I vowed to make a prediction,
so predict I shall.
Before the sun sets today,
Henry Tibbs will make his move.
Give us that long.
You have until
the end of the day.
[Cho clears throat]
Is Lisbon always this late?
She had some personal business.
[jingles]
[closes door]
Good morning.
I'm with the CBI.
I need to know
if somebody pawned
a camera here
in the past 24 hours.
'Take a look.'
A high-end DSLR in a case
with multiple lenses.
Oh, yeah.
That one came in last night.
A mangy guy brought it in.
Rotten teeth, dog breath.
That camera is evidence
in a homicide investigation.
- Where is it at now?
- Sold it.
Do you have a record
of the purchase?
Alright. How about
the memory card? You sell that?
I sell those separately.
More money for me.
That one had a 32 gig card.
I need a working digital camera.
Sure.
Thirty bucks.
I'll give you five
for a two-minute rental.
[Lisbon]
'Do you know this man?'
[Willie chuckles]
Mike Flynn.
Anger management issues.
And I know where he keeps
his bedroll, too.
- Mike Flynn?
- Get the hell out of my house!
You are Mike Flynn, right?
And y-you're
in a man's house, and I..
I'll call the police
if you don't go.
- Just calm down.
- Now!
Calm down.
We are the police.
[panting]
Sushi for lunch?
Expensive
goose-down sleeping bag?
How'd you pay for this stuff?
The streets have been
kind lately.
We need to check
your backpack, okay?
- Put it down!
- Hey. Take it easy.
Drop it.
Put it down.
I have a photo of you coming
after a murder victim
with that knife. You wanna
explain that, Mr. Flynn?
I-I don't like having
my photo taken.
[cell phone ringing]
Get your hands
behind your back.
[Rigsby]
'Now.'
[ringing continues]
- Lisbon.
- 'It's Cho.'
'I just lost Tibbs on
the freeway. He's off the grid.'
Should we be worried?
What was Tibbs doing
before Cho lost sight of him?
Driving around the city,
aimless.
As predicted, he's trying
to work up the courage.
Can't even put out
a BOLO to find him.
We can pick him on a weapons
charge for the machine gun.
Oh. Whoa.
You promised. Sunset. If
I can get inside his house
I know I can figure out
where Tibbs will go.
You'll never get a judge
to grant you a warrant.
'Wait a minute.
We don't need one.'
All we need is permission
from a homeowner.
I already told you,
I'm not getting involved.
We're not asking you to.
We need for you to cooperate.
It doesn't matter. I don't trust
you, and I'm not gonna help.
If you quit now, you're gonna
miss the best part. Payback.
What are you talking about?
A few months ago,
I had a fiance who..
- Well, he tried to kill me.
- You're lying.
Look, everybody thought
he was the greatest guy
including me,
until he pulled a gun.
What did you do?
I shot him.
Dead.
[inhales deeply]
What can I do to help?
We need to search your house.
- Nice.
- Well, it's a choice.
Lacks a woman's touch.
Got something.
[Patrick]
'Wow.'
The imagination station.
"All that's necessary
for evil to triumph
'is that good men
do nothing."'
That's, uh, Edmund Burke,
I believe.
[Lisbon]
'Wherever Tibbs is, at least
he doesn't have these with him.'
Well, he may have
other weapons.
Check this out.
[Lisbon]
'The mayor's public appearance
schedule.'
I wonder what he did
for Tibbs to target him.
Doesn't matter. All Tibbs
cares about is the rush
that comes from killing
an important man.
The mayor's power
becomes his power.
[Lisbon]
'Where is Tibbs now?'
'Who else do you think would be
a target for his rage?'
I don't know, but he hasn't
signed his divorce papers yet.
Do we have someone at the diner
where Tibbs' wife works?
[door closes]
Where is she?
Where's my wife?
Duffel bag could be a weapon.
- 'Where's my wife?'
- We need to hold back.
We move too soon, we blow
our whole cover with Tibbs.
- Can I help you?
- I don't know, man.
You helping my wife
hide from me?
Linda went home early today.
[chuckles]
She didn't go home.
She hasn't been home in weeks.
She staying with you?
You can tell me.
You hot for my wife?
You bangin'my wife?
[sighs]
I need you to go now.
Please? You're scaring
my customers.
Okay, I'll go.
Next time you see Linda..
...give her something from me.
[unzips]
Tell her to choke on these.
Well, at least
you didn't shoot this one.
If I understand
this correctly
two of my agents almost shot
a man in a crowded diner
for bringing his wife
flowers.
"Almost" is the key word there.
I've listened.
I've empathized.
I've heard enough.
Case is too dangerous.
We need a new approach.
Agreed. No more sitting around
and waiting
for something to push Tibbs
over the edge.
We need to create
our own stressor.
Are you saying, incite
the suspect to violence?
It wouldn't take much. Cut off
the power to his house
a couple of eggs on his truck.
Enough to make him go berserk,
do something violent.
You're off the case, Jane.
Actually, as a matter of fact,
there is no case.
Henry Tibbs is a sick man,
and he needs psychological help.
What if he can't be helped?
Weare the criminals then,
if we don't at least try.
- I'm taking Rigsby and Cho.
- Where?
I'm arresting Henry Tibbs
on felony weapons charges.
I wonder if our new boss
is in a little over his head.
Really? I don't.
Tibbs could kill him.
Or he could save Tibbs.
Okay, you two,
cover the back.
I'm sick of watching everyone
play with this man's life.
Yeah?
You're with
the Goldwyn Group, right?
Is this about
the job interview?
No, sir.
I'm afraid it's not.
Hi, Henry.
My name is Luther Wainright.
Hold on.
You-you were at CBI.
That's right.
We are with the government.
We've been watching you.
You what?
We spoke with your wife,
Henry.
We know you're in a lot of pain
and we're worried about you.
The government
would like to help.
Wait. Wait, wait.
What the hell is going on?
Look, I know this is all
pretty confusing
and we're gonna explain
everything.
First, however, we need
to search your house.
- I have a warrant right here.
- You don't need a warrant.
You can come inside my house.
I got nothing to hide.
- Thank you.
- Oh. Excuse me, sir.
We're busting in.
Cover the rear exit.
Hold the door.
[engine revving]
Hey. This is Wainright.
Tibbs is on the run.
Get us a bird in the air.
Hey, Jane. Tibbs evaded arrest.
He's on the move.
Okay.
You.
Hey, Henry.
[crowd gasps]
Okay. Stay calm. Don't move.
Do not draw your weapons.
This man will not hurt you.
He cannot hurt you.
No.
Isn't that right, Henry?
What the hell are you
talking about?
You don't wanna pull that
trigger. You think you do.
You think it'll switch off
that vacancy sign in your soul
but the truth is, taking
a life's just gonna make things
a whole lot more complicated.
Believe me.
I don't expect to live
past today.
But you can.
You haven't hurt anyone yet.
You put that gun away now
and we will get you
the help that you need.
I think..
I think it's too late for me..
...and everyone here.
[screaming]
Hold on, boss.
Whew.
Loud.
Hey. How ya doin'?
You're under arrest
for the attempted murder of..
...everybody. Turn around.
Put your hands on your head.
[handcuffs rattle]
What's going on?
How come no one's hurt?
When we searched Tibbs' house
we replaced all of
his live rounds with blanks
in case we lost him again.
So long, partner.
Let's go.
The DA is offering you
90 days in county jail
if you plead no contest to two
counts of theft from a body.
You'll have a warm bed
for the winter
and shelter waiting for you
when you get out.
Sounds good.
Thanks.
Oh, um, I was
in the pawnshop today
and I picked something up
I thought
maybe you could use
when you get out.
I haven't played
one of these in years.
I didn't think so.
Your lawyer's gonna be here
in a couple of minutes.
You take of yourself,
Willie.
[blinds rattle]
[saxophone music]
Uh..
That's, uh, that's
kind of...my spot.
Oh.
- Right. Sorry.
- Yeah.
- Thank you.
- Mm-hmm.
[inhales deeply and sighs]
You, uh, set me up today.
You knew I would be the stressor
that pushed Tibbs over the edge.
Well, one can never
really know these things.
To be honest,
I was rooting for you.
- Really?
- Yes.
I find your, uh,
youthful brand of earnestness
quite refreshing.
How did you know Tibbs was
gonna go to that garden?
Educated guess.
He had it circled
in his calendar.
Well, then why on earth wouldn't
you clear the area first?
The plan that was approved
by, uh...you
was to catch Tibbs
in the act, I believe.
You know that psychopathy test
I gave Tibbs?
Mm.
I figured out
why it didn't work.
See, it's a rating scale
based on observation
so the more time you spend
with the subject
the more accurately you can
then observe
their behavioral traits
and, uh, guess what
I've been doing?
Oh, you haven't.
Glibness
and superficial charm?
- Check.
- You flatter me.
- Grandiose sense of self-worth?
- You betcha.
'Cunning and manipulative,
poor behavioral controls'
failure to accept responsibility
for own actions.
So I, uh, I cross-referenced
all of my observations
with your history as a thief
and a con artist
and, uh,
congratulations, Jane.
'According to the score'
you are a clinical psychopath.
Wow.
Well...certainly explains a lot.
Now I know what
I'm dealing with
so I'll adjust accordingly.
As you should.
Lisbon.
Everything alright?
Uh, yeah. Yeah.
I like our new boss.
I think we'll work
very well together.
Would you like some tea?
I'm tired.
I'm gonna go home.
I made a pot.
Alright.
I'll take one to go.
I heard you got your man.
As did you. Nice work.
You think I'm
an antisocial personality?
Yeah. Sure. Who isn't?
Stay tuned for scenes
from our next episode.